Finding Aid for School of Dentistry (University of Michigan) Records, 1873-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Dentistry (University of Michigan) records
1873-2010
University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.
87316 BImu Bimu C121 2
The School of Dentistry is a teaching and research unit of the University of Michigan. Records include administrative files, faculty meeting minutes, curriculum and education, subject files relating to dentistry and to the professional interests of the school's faculty; and photographs and films.
34.5 linear feet in 35 boxes
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
1.3 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was first received from the School of Dentistry in 1939 (donor no. 764 ). The bulk of the records were received in 1984. Faculty minute volumes were received in 2001.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Dental School record group is open in part, boxes 12-34 are subject to the Executive Offices restriction. The Dental School record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 12-34
The College of Dental Surgery at the University of Michigan was founded by the Regents in 1875. The practicing dentists of the state were instrumental in its creation. They had originally petitioned the Regents in 1866 for the establishment of a chair of dentistry. When that petition failed to win regental approval, dentists submitted another petition in 1873. The Regents expressed a willingness to approve this second request, but claimed lack of funds made action impossible. The dentists then turned to the state legislature where they were successful in obtaining a special appropriation for the purpose of teaching dentistry at the university.
Originally dentistry was taught by two professors. They, and those subsequently appointed to the faculty, developed a college noted for the adeptness of its graduates in technical and operative areas. Throughout the nineteenth century the college's focus was primarily on technique, but at the beginning of the twentieth century research began to assume an important position in the college's activities. The first major project was undertaken by Marcus Ward, who in 1903 began a study of the properties of dental amalgams used as filling material. Research was also carried on in areas of surgical procedures, with particular success in the area of restoration. Eventually, research became a common activity among the faculty.
Throughout the twentieth century the nature of the student body and the character of the subjects taught developed and changed. In 1921 dental hygiene was first taught, largely to women who would go on to become dental assistants and technicians. By 1927, when the college was renamed the School of Dentistry, the need for both continuing education for practicing dentists and for post-graduate educational opportunities for students had been recognized and was being acted upon. The W. K. Kellogg foundation was particularly instrumental during the 1930s and 1940s in making funds and space available for these two activities.
Space was a continuing problem for the school. When it was founded, the school was placed in a university-owned house, originally used as a faculty residence. In 1877 the school was relocate into a larger building, another university-owned house originally used by a faculty member. In 1891 the school inherited the old university Hospital. During 1908 and 1909 a special building was erected for the Dental School, on North University Avenue. This building was enlarged in 1923. In 1939-1940, with funds supplied by the W. K. Kellogg Foundation and the Works Progress Administration, the W. K. Kellogg Foundation Institute: Graduate and Postgraduate Dentistry Building was constructed. In 1969, as part of a major construction program initiated the year before, the 1908 structure was razed. It was replaced by a complex of buildings completed in 1971.
Deans of the School of Dentistry
1875-1903 Jonathan Taft
1903-1906 (Acting) Cyrenus G. Darling
1907 Willoughby D. Miller
1907-1916 Nelville Hoff
1916-1934 Marcus L. Ward
1934-1935 Chalmers John Lyons
1935-1950 Russell W. Bunting
1950-1962 Paul H. Jeserich
1962-1981 William R. Mann
1981-1982 (Acting) Robert E. Doerr
1982-1987 Richard L. Christiansen
1987-1989 (Acting) William Kotowicz
1989-1995 J. Bernard Machen
1995-2002 William Kotowicz
2003-2013 Peter Polverini
2013- Peter Polverini
The School of Dentistry record group spans the years from 1873 to 2010, but does not comprehensively document the entire span. The records are fragmentary, providing only a partial picture of the School of Dentistry. Documentation reflects the tenures of various deans with scattered documents from the late 1800s and more detail in the period 1920-1990. The records give some insight into the development of dentistry as a profession, and the training and education of dental students. The records, comprised of 33.5 linear feet, have been divided into nine series: Educational Information, Administration, Organizations, Surveys, Photographs and Audiovisual Materials, Department Chairpersons' Meetings, Faculty Meetings, American Dental Association Accreditation, Dental Research Institute, and Website
Subjects:
Dentistry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dentists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Dental Research Institute.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; W. K. Kellogg Foundation.; Washtenaw County Dental Association (Mich.); Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hoff, Nelville Soule, 1854-1926.; Lyons, Chalmers John, 1874-1935.; Taft, J. (Jonathan), 1820-1903.; Ward, Marcus Llewellyn, 1875-1963.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dentistry--United States.; Offices.; School of Dentistry Building (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Educational Information
  The series Educational Information brings together information about the history of the school, its educational programs and curriculum, departments within the school, work with students, and some student notebooks and related material collected by the school over the years. Also included are some interesting publications and speeches by dentistry professors from other universities. Information on departments within the School of Dentistry reflects the structure of the school and activities of the departments from the 1960s through the 1980s.
  An outsize ledger volume of unknown provenance that was donated to the School of Dentistry, details the dental practice of Dr. James [likely in Kalamazoo, Michigan]. The volume contains patient records from this practice dating from 1873 to 1895.
  The Educational Information series is comprised of two chronologically defined subseries, 1875-1989 and ca. 1956- 1997, reflecting different accessions. The 1956- 1997 subseries is restricted under Executive Offices rule.
  - Files, 1875-1989
    - History and General Information
      - Historical Information, 1922-1962; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - By-laws of the School of Dentistry, 1963 (Box 1)
      - Affiliation with Foreign Universities, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
      - Honor Council, undated (Box 1)
      - Michigan Dental Law, 1883-1961 (Box 1)
      - Public Health Dentistry, 1924; 1937; 1941; 1954; 1956; 1961 (Box 1)
      - Sesquicentennial Celebration, 1967 (Box 1)
      - US Schools of Dentistry, undated (Box 1)
      - Clippings
        - 1923, 1938; 1940-1949 (except 1945 and 1947) (Box 1)
        - 1950-1953 (Box 1)
          (except 1952)
        - 1962-1966, 1975 (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
        - Newspapers Advertisements (Box 1)
    - Programs
      - Affirmative Action Program, 1963-1980 (Box 1)
      - Cleft Palate Center Program, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
      - College of Literature, Science and the Arts and Dentistry Combined Curriculum, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
      - Dental Auxiliary Utilization Program, 1969-1979 (Box 1)
      - Dental Materials Program, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - Flint Public Schools, undated (Box 1)
      - General Dental Residency Program, 1974 (Box 1)
      - Graduate Program in Restorative Dentistry, 1963-1973 (Box 1)
      - Mott Dental Program, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
      - State Dental Hygienist Visits to Public Schools, 1937 (Box 1)
      - Undergraduate Curriculum, 1942-1959 (Box 1)
    - Departments
      - Crown and Bridge Department
        - Correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 1)
      - Dental Hygiene Department
        - Program Description and Curriculum, 1963-1978 (Box 1)
      - Department of Community Dentistry
        - Correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
        - Meetings, 1963 (Box 1)
      - Department of Complete Denture
        - Program Information, undated (Box 1)
      - Department of Educational Resources
        - Audio-visual Services, 1973 (Box 1)
        - Correspondence, 1972-1981 (Box 1)
        - Photographic Services, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
        - Special Project Grant Request, 1972 (Box 1)
      - Department of Occlusion
        - Correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 1)
      - Department of Operative Dentistry
        - Correspondence and Reports, 1972-1980 (Box 1)
        - Literature, undated (Box 1)
        - Review Committee, 1976 (Box 1)
      - Department of Oral Biology
        - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
        - Evaluation, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Department of Oral Diagnosis
        - Correspondence, 1960-1981 (Box 2)
        - Departmental Review Data, undated (Box 2)
      - Department of Oral Pathology
        - Program Information, 1952-1959; 1976 (Box 2)
      - Department of Oral Surgery
        - Cooperation with University Hospital, 1957-1968 (Box 2)
        - Correspondence, 1944-1982 (Box 2)
        - Literature, undated (Box 2)
        - Reports, 1956-1957; 1961; 1963 (Box 2)
        - Senior Oral Surgery Manual, undated (Box 2)
        - Statistics, 1950-1959 (Box 2)
      - Department of Orthodontics
        - Chairman of Orthodontics Search, 1965 (Box 2)
        - Center for Human Growth and Development, 1963; 1969; 1971 (Box 2)
        - Correspondence 1966-1968, 1970, 1975-1981 (except 1978 and 1980), 1966-1981 (Box 2)
        - Department Report, undated (Box 2)
        - Program Description, 1968; 1971; 1972; 1976 (Box 2)
        - Research Grant Proposal, 1965 (Box 2)
        - Undergraduate Program, 1969-1983 (Box 2)
      - Department of Pedodontics
        - Department Review Data, 1976 (Box 2)
        - Minutes of Pedodontic Staff-Meeting, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
        - Program Information, 1950; 1961; 1975 (Box 2)
      - Department of Periodontics
        - Correspondence, 1963-1964; 1970-1977 (Box 2)
      - Department of Radiology, 1959-1964
        - Yearly Report, 1959-1964 (Box 2)
      - Endodontic Department
        - Program Description, undated (Box 2)
      - Prosthetic Department
        - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 2)
      - Preclinical Department
        - Correspondence, 1976-1981 (Box 2)
      - X-Ray Department
        - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - Faculty
      - Faculty and Staff Lists, 1966 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Development Teaching Grant, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Faculty Policy on Students Awards, undated (Box 2)
      - Recommendation for Appointment to the Teaching Faculty of the Graduate School, 1948-1958 (Box 2)
      - University Distinguished Professorships, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Funding
      - American Fund for Dental Health, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
      - Capitation Grant, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
      - Graduate Training Grant, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Prepayment Program for University Students, 1960 (Box 2)
      - Priority Fund, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
      - Research Grants, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      - Training in Expanded Auxiliary Management Grant, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
    - Lecture Notes, Manuals, and Ledger
      - Dental Anatomy and Prosthetic Technics, undated (Box 2)
      - Laboratory Manual for Qualitative Analysis, undated (Box 2)
      - Chalmers John Lyons (Box 3)
        - Lecture Notes, 1920 (Box 3)
        - Photos: Pre and Post-operative Cases, 1925; 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - Ledger from Dr. James, 1873-1895 (Volume Bimu/C121)
      - John Kenneth Lyons, 1904-1948 (Box 3)
      - Jonathan Taft Lecture Notes, 1875-1900; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Materials and their Structural Uses, 1945 (Box 3)
      - Neville Soule Hoff's Course in Dental Therapeutics, 1896-1897 (Box 3)
      - Saliva and Mucus Tests, undated (Box 3)
    - National Board Dental Examinations, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Project Proposals, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Research Project: "An integrated Teaching Program in Dental Education,", 1960 (Box 3)
    - Publications and Speeches
      - "A Prospectus on Dental Education" by John B. Macdonald, 1956 (Box 3)
      - William R. Davis
        - "Choosing a Dentist,", 1923 (Box 3)
        - Speeches and Publications, undated (Box 3)
      - U. Garfield Rickert papers, 1933 (Box 3)
      - The Dental Journal, 1902 (Box 3)
      - "The Teaching of Social or Community Dentistry" by Edith R. Sanders, 1965 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous Publications, undated (Box 3)
      - William Haber Speeches: "Authority without Freedom, undated (Box 3)
      - Reginald Sullens Speech: "A Plane or Solid Life?", 1961 (Box 3)
      - C. Gordon Watson: "In your Hands,", 1975 (Box 3)
    - Students Information
      - Absence Records, 1914-1917 (Box 3)
      - Dental Career Day, 1964-1979 (Box 4)
      - Expenses, 1922-1925; 1949 (Box 4)
      - Grades, 1885-1886 (Box 4)
      - Internship Correspondence, 1933 (Box 4)
      - Orientation, 1938-1969 (Box 4)
      - Student Notebook
        - Augustine L. Steger: Dental Surgery Class, 1900 (Box 4)
        - A. W. Hogan: Bacteriology and Drawings, undated (Box 4)
        - Ralph J. Roper: Dental Surgery Class, 1897-1898 (Box 4)
      - Student Table Clinic Day, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
      - The Dental Students Magazine, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Files, circa 1956-1997
    - Curriculum
      - Anatomy (Box 30)
        [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2025 ]
      - Anesthesiology (Box 30)
      - Basic Techniques (Box 30)
      - Biochemistry (Box 30)
      - Complete Denture (Box 30)
      - Crown and Bridge (Box 30)
      - Dental Hygiene (Box 30)
      - Dental Materials (Box 30)
      - Dental Pharmacology (Box 30)
      - Dental Prosthodontics (Box 30)
      - Emergencies (Box 30)
      - Endodontics (Box 30)
      - History of Dentistry (Box 30)
      - Oral Diagnosis (Box 30)
      - Oral Histology (Box 30)
      - Oral Surgery (Box 30)
      - Pedodontics (Box 30)
      - Radiographic Technics (Box 30)
    - Departments
      - Preclinical Department
        - Reports, 1975-1981 (Box 30)
        - Reports, 1981-1986 (Box 30)
        - Mission (Box 30)
      - Biological and Materials Sciences
        - Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 30)
        - Program Description (Box 30)
      - Community Dentistry
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 30)
        - Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 30)
        - Objectives and Mission (Box 30)
      - Complete Denture and Prosthodontics
        - Addendums (Box 30)
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 30)
        - Correspondence (Box 30)
        - Departmental Review Data (Box 30)
        - Mission (Box 30)
      - Continuing Education
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1984 (Box 30)
        - Annual Reports, 1984-1989 (Box 30)
        - Financials, 1981-1987 (Box 30)
        - Role (Box 30)
      - Crown and Bridge
        - Annual Reports, 1975-1983 (Box 31)
        - Annual Reports, 1983-1988 (Box 31)
        - Departmental Review, 1978 (Box 31)
      - Dental Auxiliary Utilization (Box 31)
        - Annual Reports, 1969-1975 (Box 31)
        - Departmental Review, 1980 (Box 31)
      - Dental Hygiene
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 31)
        - Departmental Review, 1979 (Box 31)
        - Objectives (Box 31)
      - Dental Laboratory
        - Annual Reports, 1971-1984 (Box 31)
      - Dental Materials
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 31)
        - Departmental Review, 1978 (Box 31)
        - Mission (Box 31)
      - Director of Clinics
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1986 (Box 31)
      - Educational Resources
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1987; 2 folders (Box 31)
        - Departmental Review (Box 31)
        - Special Equipment Expenses and Reports, 1956-1959 (Box 31)
      - Endodontics
        - Annual Reports, 1973-1988 (Box 31)
        - Departmental Review, 1977 (Box 31)
        - Mission (Box 31)
      - Health Service
        - Annual Reports, 1978-1980 (Box 31)
        - Objectives (Box 31)
      - Hospital Dental Service
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1987 (Box 31)
        - Correspondence (Box 31)
        - Departmental Review and Reports (Box 31)
        - Mission (Box 31)
      - Library
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 32)
      - Occlusion
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 32)
        - Departmental Report, 1979 (Box 32)
        - Mission (Box 32)
      - Operative Dentistry
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 32)
        - Departmental Review, 1976 (Box 32)
        - Roles (Box 32)
      - Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1982 (Box 32)
        - Annual Reports, 1982-1988 (Box 32)
        - Departmental Review, 1980 (Box 32)
        - Mission (Box 32)
        - Scope of Practice Report (Box 32)
        - Staff Meeting Minutes, 1979 (Box 32)
      - Oral Biology
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1977 (Box 32)
        - Annual Reports, 1977-1983 (Box 32)
        - Annual Reports, 1983-1988 (Box 32)
        - Mission Statement (Box 32)
        - PhD Materials (Box 32)
      - Oral Diagnosis and Radiology
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 32)
        - Departmental Review, 1971-1976 (Box 32)
        - Mission (Box 32)
      - Oral Medicine/Pathology/Surgery
        - Annual Report, 1988-1989 (Box 33)
        - Departmental Report, 1987 (Box 33)
      - Oral Pathology
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 33)
        - Departmental Review and Evaluation (Box 33)
        - Mission (Box 33)
      - Orthodontics and Pediatric Dentistry
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 33)
        - Annual Report, 1988-1989 (Box 33)
        - Departmental Reports, 1988 (Box 33)
        - Objectives (Box 33)
      - Partial Denture
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1988 (Box 33)
        - Departmental Review Materials (Box 33)
      - Pedodontics
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1980 (Box 33)
        - Annual Reports, 1980-1988 (Box 33)
        - Departmental Review Data, 1976 (Box 33)
        - Departmental Review Data, 1979 (Box 33)
        - Mission (Box 33)
      - Periodontics
        - Annual Reports, 1974-1982 (Box 33)
        - Mission (Box 33)
      - Prevention and Health Care
        - Departmental Report, 1989 (Box 33)
      - Prosthodontics
        - Annual Report, 1988-1989 (Box 33)
        - Annual Report, 1996; 1997 (Box 33)
        - Complete Fixed Prosthodontics Mission (Box 33)
        - Fixed Prosthodontics Program, 1977 (Box 33)
        - "Plan for the Future,", 1988 (Box 34)
        - Removable Partial Prosthodontics Mission (Box 34)
      - Publications Department
        - Correspondence (Box 34)
      - Restorative Dentistry
        - Annual Report, 1988-1989 (Box 34)
      - Undergraduate Orthodontics
        - Departmental Review, 1977-1978 (Box 34)
- Administration, 1899-1999
  The series Administration (1899-1999, 14.3 linear feet) includes administrative information on topics such as admissions, interaction with other university units, committees, evaluations of faculty and administration, reports, and finances during the period from 1899 to 1999. In addition, this series contains records from eight deans of the School of Dentistry: Russell W. Bunting, Paul H. Jeserich, William R. Mann, Marcus L. Ward, Robert E. Doerr, Richard L. Christiansen, William Kotowicz, and J. Bernard Machen. The Dean's files are comprised mainly of correspondence, although some speeches and publications and a small amount of biographical information will also be found here. Other material in this series includes background on the W. K. Kellogg Foundation Institute, and information on dental activities in Latin America covering 1944-1974.
  - Files, circa 1918-circa 1985
    - Administrative Information
      - Admissions
        - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 4)
        - Study Proposal: "Selecting a Dental Student,", 1968 (Box 4)
      - CAIDENT Computer Center, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Cooperation with University Units
        - College of Engineering, 1932-1934 (Box 4)
        - Department of Anatomy, 1928-1951 (Box 4)
        - Department of Internal Medicine, 1934-1939 (Box 4)
        - Department of Zoology, 1920-1926 (Box 4)
        - Pathology, undated (Box 4)
        - Physiology Department, 1961-1971 (Box 4)
        - School of Public Health, 1973-1982 (Box 4)
      - Dental Building
        - Groundbreaking and Dedication, 1962-1971 (Box 4)
        - Proposed Addition, 1955 (Box 4)
      - Dental Library
        - Correspondence, 1932-1966 (Box 4)
      - Dental School Loaned Instrument Program, 1944-1949 (Box 4)
      - Hospital Dentistry
        - Correspondence (except 1974), 1969-1979; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Medical Service Plan (Oral Surgery), 1977 (Box 4)
        - Minutes, 1971-1979 (Box 4)
        - Reports, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
      - Plan of Dental School Management, undated (Box 4)
      - University Hospital Service of Dentistry and Dental Oral Surgery, 1964-1967 (Box 4)
      - Vice-President and Chief Financial Officer Correspondence, 1953-1978 (Box 4)
      - Vice-President for Academic Affairs Correspondence, 1964-1972 (Box 4)
      - Virginia Medical College
        - Correspondence, 1921-1945 (Box 4)
    - Committees
      - Academic Support Committee, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Ad Hoc Committee List, 1963-1967 (Box 4)
      - Animal Care Committee, 1965 (Box 4)
      - Committee on Clinical Research and Investigation Involving Human Beings, undated (Box 4)
      - Committee on Outside Institutional Relations, 1964 (Box 4)
      - Committee on Preventative Dentistry, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Committee on Professional Appearance of Students, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
      - Committee on Teaching, 1962-1966 (Box 4)
      - Curriculum Committee
        - Correspondence 1958-1965 (except 1961 and 1964) (Box 4)
        - Course Outlines, 1959-1963 (Box 4)
        - Curricular Revisions (except 1962), 1960-1963 (Box 4)
      - Dean's Committee, 1966-1974; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Development and Planning Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee
        - Correspondence, 1933; 1935; 1938; 1962 (Box 4)
        - Meetings, 1962-1969; 6 folders (Box 4)
      - General Research Support Grant Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
      - Graduate Studies Committee, 1962-1967 (Box 5)
      - Homecoming Committee, 1963-1967 (Box 5)
      - Honors Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
      - Library Committee, 1962-1967 (Box 5)
      - Oral Diagnosis Committee, 1958 (Box 5)
      - Photographic Committee, 1957-1967 (Box 5)
      - Promotions Committee, 1954-1964; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Records Committee
        - Meetings, 1957-1958; 1966; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Research Committee
        - Correspondence, 1954-1967 (Box 5)
        - Minutes, 1957-1963 (Box 5)
      - Special Services Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
      - Students Affairs Committee, 1962-1966 (Box 5)
      - Table Clinic Committee, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Dean's Files
      - Bunting, Russell W.
        - Correspondence
          - Alumni (except 1948), 1945-1949 (Box 5)
          - American College of Dentists, 1938-1948 (Box 5)
          - American Dental Association, 1942 (Box 5)